<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>continuum</title>
<link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>random notes and daily miscellany</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.361</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>PechaKucha &amp; Haiku</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-16/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="what-is-pechakucha" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-pechakucha">What is PechaKucha?</h2>
<p>Dytham and Klein developed a new form of presenting they have dubbed “pecha kucha” (Japanese for “chatter”). This form of presentation style has a simple set of rules—exactly 20 slides displayed for 20 seconds each. Say what you need to say in six minutes and forty seconds.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PechaKucha">this link</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-a-haiku" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-a-haiku">What is a Haiku?</h2>
<p>The haiku is a Japanese poetic form that consists of three lines, with five syllables in the first line, seven in the second, and five in the third. The haiku developed from the hokku, the opening three lines of a longer poem known as a tanka. The haiku became a separate form of poetry in the 17th century.</p>
<p>The haiku began gaining mainstream recognition outside Japan in the early 20th century. In the English-speaking world, the form was popularized by Imagists such as Ezra Pound and later by Beat poets such as Allen Ginsberg.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://www.britannica.com/art/haiku">this link</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Notes</category>
  <category>Japan</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-16/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On Human Stupidity</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-15/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="the-fourth-law-of-stupidity" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-fourth-law-of-stupidity">The Fourth Law of Stupidity</h2>
<p>Non-stupid people always underestimate the damaging power of stupid people. In particular, they constantly forget that at all times and places and under any circumstances to deal and/or associate with stupid people infallibly turns out to be a costly mistake. <span class="citation" data-cites="cipolla2021">Cipolla and Taleb (2021)</span></p>
<p>Helpless people are through their own nature will fail to recognize how dangerous stupid people are. Intelligent people and bandits also are tempted to believe or associate themselves with a stupid individual. However this can have a disastrous effects:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>It is based on a complete misunderstanding of the essential nature of stupidity,</li>
<li>It gives the stupid person added scope for the exercise of his gifts.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="avoid-stupid-people" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="avoid-stupid-people">Avoid Stupid People</h2>
<p>Because of the erratic behavior of the stupid, one cannot foresee all the stupid’s actions and reactions, and before long one will be pulverized by the unpredictable moves of the stupid partner.</p>
</section>
<section id="history" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="history">History</h2>
<p>In public and private life, innumerable individuals have failed to understand the Fourth Law. The failure has caused incalculable losses in the history of mankind.</p>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">




</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-cipolla2021" class="csl-entry">
Cipolla, Carlo M., and Nassim Nicholas Taleb. 2021. <em>The Basic Laws of Human Stupidity</em>. New York: Doubleday.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Notes</category>
  <category>Philosophy</category>
  <category>Life</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-15/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On Human Stupidity</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-15a/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="the-fifth-law-of-stupidity" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-fifth-law-of-stupidity">The Fifth Law of Stupidity</h2>
<p>A stupid person is the most dangerous type of person and they are more dangerous then bandits. The worst consequences of this at macro level is that the algebraic sum of the stupid individuals in a group or society at large will affect the wealth and welfare of the society. <span class="citation" data-cites="cipolla2021">Cipolla and Taleb (2021)</span></p>
</section>
<section id="macro-analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="macro-analysis">Macro Analysis</h2>
<p>Bandits: The net result of the action is simply the transfer of positives and negatives. The society as whole neither better nor worse off. If all members of a society were perfect bandits, the society would remain stagnant but there would be no major disaster.</p>
<p>Stupids: They cause losses to other people with no gain on their own account. The society as a whole is impoverished. (See the First Basic Law <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma">, the fraction of stupid is a constant and the Second Basic Law, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma"> is not affected by time, space, race, class or any other sociocultural or historical variable).</p>
</section>
<section id="essential-points" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="essential-points">Essential Points</h2>
<p>In a poorly performing society:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>the stupid are allowed by the other members to become more active and take more actions.</li>
<li>there is a decline in the composition of non-stupid people, for example H<sub>s</sub> and B<sub>s</sub> population will decline the society.</li>
</ol>
<p>Therefore:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>In a group, society or country moving uphill, intelligent people manage to keep the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma"> fraction at bay and produce enough gains to make progress a certainty.</li>
<li>In a group, society or country moving downhill, the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma"> fraction is still the same but the composition of non-stupid people increases the destructive power and makes decline a certainty. This is the direction to Hell.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">




</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-cipolla2021" class="csl-entry">
Cipolla, Carlo M., and Nassim Nicholas Taleb. 2021. <em>The Basic Laws of Human Stupidity</em>. New York: Doubleday.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Notes</category>
  <category>Philosophy</category>
  <category>Life</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-15a/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Random Notes</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-14/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="imprecision" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="imprecision">Imprecision</h2>
<p>The margin of imprecision is bound to affect the measurement but it does not affect the essence of the argument. <span class="citation" data-cites="cipolla2021">Cipolla and Taleb (2021)</span></p>
</section>
<section id="vacation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="vacation">Vacation</h2>
<p>Vacation is when you forget what day it is and I can hardly tell what day it was when we were travelling to Tofino.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Relaxing brings weakness, when done by a muscle; but brings strength, when done by a person.” ― Mokokoma Mokhonoana</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="focusing-illusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="focusing-illusion">Focusing Illusion</h2>
<p>The idea that you can be focused on a particular aspect of life, so much so that you can believe that your whole happiness depends on it. In having a focusing illusion, you create your own reason for feeling unhappy. <span class="citation" data-cites="mogi2018">Mogi (2018)</span></p>
<p>If unhappiness is a vacuum in which the required element is absent, the vacuum is created by the biased imagination of the subject. There is no absolute formula for happiness - each unique condition of life can serve as the foundation for happiness in its own unique way. <span class="citation" data-cites="mogi2018">Mogi (2018)</span></p>
</section>
<section id="how-to-fix" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-fix">How to Fix?</h2>
<p>From Seth’s blog (<a href="https://seths.blog/2023/05/the-thing-about-decay/">link</a>)</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>One reason we have so much trouble fixing chronic degenerative conditions is that we need to remove elements before we can start building new functions. If we simply put effort on top of a shaky foundation, it’ll all be wasted. The best way forward might be to take a few steps back.</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">




</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-cipolla2021" class="csl-entry">
Cipolla, Carlo M., and Nassim Nicholas Taleb. 2021. <em>The Basic Laws of Human Stupidity</em>. New York: Doubleday.
</div>
<div id="ref-mogi2018" class="csl-entry">
Mogi, Ken. 2018. <em>The Little Book of Ikigai: The secret Japanese way to live a happy and long life</em>. London: Hodder.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Notes</category>
  <category>Flow state</category>
  <category>Philosophy</category>
  <category>Life</category>
  <category>Perfectionism</category>
  <category>Mokhonoana</category>
  <category>Mogi</category>
  <category>Cipolla</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-14/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Human Stupidity</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-13/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="the-third-law-of-stupidity" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-third-law-of-stupidity">The Third Law of Stupidity</h2>
<p>Reasonable people have q hard time imagining unreasonable behavior. A stupid person is one who causes harm to others while gaining nothing and even harming himself in doing so. (See <span class="citation" data-cites="cipolla2021">Cipolla and Taleb (2021)</span>)</p>
<p>A stupid person will harass you with no reason. You have no rational way of telling if and when and how and why the stupid creature attacks. When confronted with a stupid individual, you’re completely at his mercy. Because the stupid person’s actions do not conform to the rules of rationality. From all that proceeds:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>You’re caught by surprise.</li>
<li>You cannot build a rational defense because the attack lacks any rational structure.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="frequency-distribution" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="frequency-distribution">Frequency Distribution</h2>
<p>Most people do not act consistently, they will act intelligently one time and helplessly another. Stupid people normally show perfect consistency in all fields of human endeavors.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="cipolla2021">Cipolla and Taleb (2021)</span> classify four types of people, comments are mine:</p>
<ul>
<li>Helpless: Identify and help the helpless.</li>
<li>Intelligent: Identify and surround yourself with intelligent people.</li>
<li>Bandit: Identify and utilize bandits with great caution when circumstances demand it.</li>
<li>Stupid: Identify and isolate stupid people from your daily life, especially at work.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="stupidity-and-power" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stupidity-and-power">Stupidity and Power</h2>
<p>Damaging potential of stupidity is a function of:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Genetic factors and the resulting inheritance</li>
<li>The position of power and consequences</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="key-takeaways" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h2>
<p>The world has changed but the fraction <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma"><sup>1</sup> is till maintained. In Industrial world, class and caste have turned into politics and bureaucracy and the religion has faded away:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<div>
<pre class="mermaid mermaid-js">graph LR;
    id1(Industrial World)--&gt;Class;
    id1(Industrial World)--&gt;Caste;
    Class--&gt;Banished;
    Caste--&gt;Banished;
</pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<div>
<pre class="mermaid mermaid-js">graph LR;
    id1(Industrial World)--&gt;Politics;
    id1(Industrial World)--&gt;Bureaucracy;
    Politics--&gt;Persists;
    Bureaucracy--&gt;Persists;
</pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Also see: <a href="https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-11/">The Basic Laws of Human Stupidity</a></p>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">




</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-cipolla2021" class="csl-entry">
Cipolla, Carlo M., and Nassim Nicholas Taleb. 2021. <em>The Basic Laws of Human Stupidity</em>. New York: Doubleday.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Fraction of stupid people within a population is denoted by the symbol <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Csigma">. No specific numerical value is assigned as a numerical estimate would likely be an underestimate.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Notes</category>
  <category>Philosophy</category>
  <category>Life</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-13/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Case for Daydreaming</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-12/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="default-mode-network" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="default-mode-network">Default Mode Network</h2>
<p>In neuroscience, the&nbsp;default mode network&nbsp;(DMN), also known as the&nbsp;default network,&nbsp;default state network is best known for being active when a person is not focused on the outside world and the brain is at&nbsp;wakeful rest, such as during&nbsp;daydreaming and&nbsp;mind-wandering. It can also be active during detailed thoughts related to external task performance. Other times that the DMN is active include when the individual is thinking about others, thinking about themselves, remembering the past, and planning for the future. (See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Default_mode_network">Default mode network</a>)</p>
</section>
<section id="mind-wandering" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mind-wandering">Mind-wandering</h2>
<p>Mind-wandering is a broad term with no currently universal definition. According to McMillan, Kaufmann and Singer (2013) mind-wandering consists of 3 different subtypes: positive constructive daydreaming, guilty fear of failure, and poor attentional control. Whereas Smallwood and Schooler (2015) suggest that mind-wandering consists of thoughts that are task-unrelated and stimulus-independent. In general, a folk explanation of mind-wandering could be described as the experience of thoughts not remaining on a single topic for a long period of time, particularly when people are engaged in an attention-demanding task. (See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mind-wandering">Mind-wandering</a>)</p>
</section>
<section id="key-takeaways-from-ubc-magazine" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-takeaways-from-ubc-magazine">Key Takeaways from UBC Magazine</h2>
<p>In a cumulative and worrying way, the smart phones might be making us stupid.</p>
<p>This is no mere speculation. On the increasingly rare occasion when we let our minds wander, the blood in our brains rushes to what is called the default network.</p>
<p>The default network: a vital support centre for spontaneous thought, a creative space that helps us through our thoughts and experiences. But goal driven thinking happens in another part of the brain, disconnects us from the fullness of our experience. (See <a href="https://psych.ubc.ca/profile/kalina-christoff/">Kalina Christoff)</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Notes</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-12/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On Human Stupidity</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-11/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="the-basic-laws-of-human-stupidity" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-basic-laws-of-human-stupidity">The Basic Laws of Human Stupidity</h2>
<p>The basic laws assert that <span class="citation" data-cites="cipolla2021">Cipolla and Taleb (2021)</span></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>There will always be more stupid people than you think</p></li>
<li><p>The proportion of stupid people is invariant to intellectual, social or geographic segmentation</p></li>
<li><p>A stupid person is a person who causes losses to another person or to a group of persons while himself deriving no gain and possibly incurring losses</p></li>
<li><p>Non-stupid people always underestimate the damaging power of stupid individuals</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">




</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-cipolla2021" class="csl-entry">
Cipolla, Carlo M., and Nassim Nicholas Taleb. 2021. <em>The Basic Laws of Human Stupidity</em>. New York: Doubleday.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Notes</category>
  <category>Carlo M. Cipolla</category>
  <category>Nassim Nicholas Taleb</category>
  <category>Philosophy</category>
  <category>Life</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-11/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Negative Utility</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-10/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>You need a book, a pen, and time. More tools give you negative utility. They won’t make the work go faster. But they will consume as much time as you are willing to waste. Productivity advice</p>
<p>Do the work.</p>
<p>That’s all the productivity advice you need, and the only useful productivity advice you’re ever going to get.</p>
<p>You can direct your attention to a million optimization— email, meetings, notes, calendar, time tracking, goals, to-do lists, time estimates, prioritization frameworks, quantified self sensors, analytics, apps, documents, journaling.</p>
<p>But don’t. Ignore all this, and do the work. When you do the work, everything else optimizes itself.</p>
<p><em>Source unknown.</em></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Notes</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-10/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Truth-default Theory</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-9/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Proposed by philosophers and recently supported by experimental psychologists, there’s considerable evidence showing that if we hear something, we assume it to be true. This tendency is sometimes referred to as <strong>truth-default theory</strong>.</p>
<section id="truth-bias" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="truth-bias">Truth Bias</h3>
<p>Truth bias is people’s inclination towards believing, to some degree, the communication of another person, regardless of whether or not that person is actually lying or being untruthful It is human nature to believe communication is honest, which in turn makes humans highly vulnerable to deception. Consequently, a person’s ability to detect deception is weakened, particularly when the source of deception is unfamiliar. As long as a person already has the perception that everything they are told is true, they are still considered to be truth-biased. (See “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truth-default_theory">Truth Bias</a>”).</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Truth</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-9/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Human Soul Degrades</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-8/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="the-human-soul-degrades" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-human-soul-degrades">The Human Soul Degrades</h2>
<p>When the soul is overpowered by pleasure or pain.</p>
<p>When the soul puts on a mask and does or says something artificial or false. <span class="citation" data-cites="aurelius2003">Aurelius (2003)</span></p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-aurelius2003" class="csl-entry">
Aurelius, Marcus. 2003. <em>Meditations: A New Translation</em>. Translated by Gregory Hays. Revised ed. edition. New York: Modern Library.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Marcus Aurelius</category>
  <category>Philosophy</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-8/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Effort vs Results</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-7a/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Do not confuse effort with results.</p>
<p>Just because you put in the effort does not mean you’ll get the desired result.</p>
<p>A lot of effort gets undone long before results are felt. Going to the gym is undone if you eat poorly. Focusing only on work gets undone by the inevitable health and relationship issues that come from under-investment. When we try to speed up the outcome, our lack of patience undoes the result.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Caution
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Results are accumulated in drops but lost in buckets.Make sure you’re not undoing the things you’re trying to accomplish.</p>
</div>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Sometimes the hardest decisions a person can make will most likely lead to the best outcomes. - Colleen Hoover.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>🆚</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Notes</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-7a/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ultimate Satisfaction</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-7/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Success or failure is not relevant but the ultimate satisfaction is the process of performing those small rituals. <span class="citation" data-cites="mogi2018">Mogi (2018)</span></p>
<p>Also <a href="../../posts/2023-May-27/index.html">see Zanshin</a></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-mogi2018" class="csl-entry">
Mogi, Ken. 2018. <em>The Little Book of Ikigai: The secret Japanese way to live a happy and long life</em>. London: Hodder.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Ikigai</category>
  <category>Japan</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-7/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Fake News</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-7b/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The greatest worry about the idea of fake news isn’t actually that people believe false news - it’s that they stop believing real news. Phillips (2020)</p>
<section id="reference" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reference">Reference</h3>
<p>Phillips, T. (2020).&nbsp;<em>Truth: a brief history of total bullsh</em>t*.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Notes</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-7b/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Nocturne A2</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-6/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="practice" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practice">Practice</h2>
<p>Tempo: Free bpm.<br>
Measures: 10-17</p>
</section>
<section id="fender-stratocaster" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fender-stratocaster">Fender Stratocaster</h2>
<p>Pickup Position: Neck<br>
Master Volume: ~6<br>
Master Tone: ~6</p>
</section>
<section id="multi-effects-processor-zoom-g3xn" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="multi-effects-processor-zoom-g3xn">Multi Effects Processor: Zoom G3Xn</h2>
<p>Master Volume: 100<br>
Compressor: 5, Fast, 5, 70 ON<br>
Slab Back Delay: 20, 50, 50, Quarter note<br>
Tremolo: Tube, 30, 50, 80 OFF</p>
</section>
<section id="joyo-tremolo" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="joyo-tremolo">Joyo Tremolo</h2>
<p>Intensity: 75%<br>
Rate: 75%</p>
</section>
<section id="amplifier-fender-blues-jr.-iii" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="amplifier-fender-blues-jr.-iii">Amplifier: Fender Blues Jr.&nbsp;III</h2>
<p>Volume: 8.0<br>
Fat: OFF<br>
Treble: 6.5<br>
Bass: 6.5<br>
Middle: 6.5<br>
Master: 3.0<br>
Reverb: 5.0</p>
</section>
<section id="microphone" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="microphone">Microphone</h2>
<p>Blue Yeti<br>
Gain: 11 o’clock<br>
Mode: Omnidirectional, on desk near plant</p>
</section>
<section id="video" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="video">Video</h2>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0IJ6ceTkQbQ" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Stratocaster</category>
  <category>Hybrid picking</category>
  <category>Song</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-6/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Novelist as a Vocation</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-6a/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="new-book" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-book">New Book</h2>
<p>Novelist as a Vocation by <span class="citation" data-cites="murakami2022">Murakami (2022)</span></p>
</section>
<section id="excerpt.-reprinted-by-permission.-all-rights-reserved1." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="excerpt.-reprinted-by-permission.-all-rights-reserved1."><strong>Excerpt. © Reprinted by permission. All rights reserved</strong><sup>1</sup><strong>.</strong></h2>
<p>Writing fiction is an entirely personal process that takes place in a closed room. Shut away in a study, you sit at a desk and (in most cases) create an imaginary story out of nothing and put it in the form of writing. The formless and subjective is transformed into something tangible and objec-tive (or at least something that seeks to be objective). Defined sim-ply, this is the day-to-day work we novelists perform.I’m sure there are many people who will say, “But wait, I don’t have anything like a study.” The same was true for me when I started out writing—I had nothing resembling a study to work in. In my tiny apartment near the Hatonomori Hachiman Shrine in Sendagaya (in a building that’s since been torn down) I sat at the kitchen table late at night after my wife had gone to bed, scratching away with a pen on Japanese-style manuscript paper. That’s how I&nbsp;wrote my first two novels, Hear the Wind Sing and Pinball, 1973. “Kitchen-table” fiction is what I’ve dubbed these early works.<br>
<br>
When I first started writing Norwegian Wood, I wrote at cafés in various places in Greece, on board ferry boats, in the wait-ing lobbies of airports, in shady spots in parks, and at desks in cheap hotels. Hauling around oversized, four-hundred-character- per-page Japanese manuscript paper was too much, so in Rome I bought a cheap notebook (the kind we used to call college-ruled notebooks) and wrote the novel down in tiny writing with a dis-posable Bic pen. I still had to contend with noisy cafés, wobbly tables that made writing difficult, coffee spilling on the pages, and at night in my hotel room when I’d go over what I’d written, some-times there would be couples getting all hot and heavy beyond the paper-thin walls separating my room from the room next door. Things weren’t easy, in other words. I can smile at these memories now, but at the time it was all pretty discouraging. I had trouble finding a decent place to live, and moved all over Europe, all the while continuing to work on my novel. And I still have that thick old notebook, with its coffee stains (or whatever they are; I’m not really sure about some of them).<br>
<br>
Wherever a person is when he writes a novel, it’s a closed room, a portable study. That’s what I’m trying to say.</p>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">




</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-murakami2022" class="csl-entry">
Murakami, Haruki. 2022. <em>Novelist as a Vocation</em>. Translated by Philip Gabriel and Ted Goossen. Bond Street Books.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p><a href="https://www.amazon.ca/Novelist-as-Vocation-Haruki-Murakami-ebook/dp/B09S3LBFHS/ref=sr_1_5?adgrpid=1350200510852514&amp;hvadid=84388043562554&amp;hvbmt=be&amp;hvdev=c&amp;hvlocphy=5076&amp;hvnetw=s&amp;hvqmt=e&amp;hvtargid=kwd-84387701647169%3Aloc-32&amp;hydadcr=14268_13443533&amp;keywords=murakami&amp;qid=1686093519&amp;s=digital-text&amp;sr=1-5">link</a>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Notes</category>
  <category>Haruki Murakami</category>
  <category>Japan</category>
  <category>Fiction</category>
  <category>Life</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-6a/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Good Enough</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-5/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The perfect is the enemy of the good, often attributed to Voltaire. Yet we strive for the perfect and fail to achieve simple results. Perfectionism gets in the way of doing good stuff, ironically progress is hindered.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Perfectionism</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-5/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Anger &amp; Wholesome Way</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-4/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Anger hurts you instead of the problem that generates it.</p>
<p>Thus, try to maintain a merely disappointed and annoyed attitude.</p>
<p>A more wholesome way to make a change, instead of becoming minimalist, vegan or move into a tiny house.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Philosophy</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-4/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Book of Five Rings</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-3/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="one-sentence-summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="one-sentence-summary">One Sentence Summary</h2>
<p>Book Title <span class="citation" data-cites="musashi2005">Musashi (2005)</span></p>
</section>
<section id="key-takeaways" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipisci elit, sed eiusmod tempor incidunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrum exercitationem ullam corporis suscipit laboriosam, nisi ut aliquid ex ea commodi consequatur. Quis aute iure reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. Excepteur sint obcaecat cupiditat non proident, sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollit anim id est laborum.</li>
<li>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipisci elit, sed eiusmod tempor incidunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrum exercitationem ullam corporis suscipit laboriosam, nisi ut aliquid ex ea commodi consequatur. Quis aute iure reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. Excepteur sint obcaecat cupiditat non proident, sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollit anim id est laborum.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="miscellaneous-notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="miscellaneous-notes">Miscellaneous Notes</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipisci elit, sed eiusmod tempor incidunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrum exercitationem ullam corporis suscipit laboriosam, nisi ut aliquid ex ea commodi consequatur. Quis aute iure reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. Excepteur sint obcaecat cupiditat non proident, sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollit anim id est laborum.</p></li>
<li><p>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipisci elit, sed eiusmod tempor incidunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrum exercitationem ullam corporis suscipit laboriosam, nisi ut aliquid ex ea commodi consequatur. Quis aute iure reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. Excepteur sint obcaecat cupiditat non proident, sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollit anim id est laborum.</p></li>
</ul>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-musashi2005" class="csl-entry">
Musashi, Miyamoto. 2005. <em>The Book of Five Rings: A Classic Text on the Japanese Way of the Sword</em>. Translated by Thomas Cleary. Reissue edition. Shambhala.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Miyamoto Musashi</category>
  <category>Japan</category>
  <category>Non-fiction</category>
  <category>Life</category>
  <category>Philosophy</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-3/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Art of Practicing</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-2/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="one-sentence-summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="one-sentence-summary">One Sentence Summary</h2>
<p>The Art of Practicing by <span class="citation" data-cites="bruser1999">Bruser and Menuhin (1999)</span> contains wisdom and practical advise. Performance as a practice see page 216.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-ten-step-approach" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-ten-step-approach">A Ten-Step Approach</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Stretch</li>
<li>Settle down in your environment: Be present, correct posture, breathing.</li>
<li>Tune into your heart: Recalling profound feelings is how to tune into your heart.</li>
<li>Use your body in a comfortable and natural way. Mechanics, habits and emotions…</li>
<li>Follow your curiosity as you practice.</li>
<li>Recognize three styles of struggle:
<ol type="1">
<li>Overstated passion, in which we cling to the music.</li>
<li>Avoidance, in which we resist dealing with the music.</li>
<li>Aggression, in which we attack the music.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Drop your attitudes and be simple.</li>
<li>Apply three listening techniques:
<ol type="1">
<li>Sing the notes and lines.</li>
<li>Place your attention on the vibrations.</li>
<li>Place your attention on each sound as it resonates in the space around you.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Organize notes into groups, phrases, and textures.</li>
<li>Place your attention on the sensations of touch and movement.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="key-takeaways" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h2>
<ul>
<li>Relax, tension is your worst enemy</li>
<li>Hear the music you’re playing</li>
<li>Be gentle to yourself</li>
<li>Do not over practice, short mindful work is superior to long laboured practice sessions.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="miscellaneous-notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="miscellaneous-notes">Miscellaneous Notes</h2>
<ul>
<li>Swing the music instead of sounding like sewing machine. Group notes and play them by creating a forward motion.</li>
<li>Focus on more on the sensations of touch and movement and use your vision mainly to check that what you feel is in accord with what you see. Bruser &amp; Menuhin (1999, p.&nbsp;200).</li>
<li>Think the sound you make. Then discover the sensation your brain has created for you. Bruser &amp; Menuhin (1999, p.&nbsp;201).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">




</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-bruser1999" class="csl-entry">
Bruser, Madeline, and Yehudi Menuhin. 1999. <em>The Art of Practicing: A Guide to Making Music from the Heart</em>. Illustrated edition. New York, NY: Crown.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Madeline Bruser</category>
  <category>Non-fiction</category>
  <category>Flow state</category>
  <category>Philosophy</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-2/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Killing Commendatore</title>
  <link>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-1/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="brief-summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="brief-summary">Brief Summary</h2>
<p>A story of a painter who did portrait commissions for financial stability and later spent several months in solitude to paint as he pleased. Loaded with Murakami characters and wisdom, the book inspires to pursue some form of art for one’s own satisfaction, live in solitude, get better at what one does and make art. <span class="citation" data-cites="murakami2019">Murakami (2019)</span></p>
</section>
<section id="key-takeaways" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h2>
<p>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet.</p>
</section>
<section id="miscellaneous-notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="miscellaneous-notes">Miscellaneous Notes</h2>
<p>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet…</p>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">




</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-murakami2019" class="csl-entry">
Murakami, Haruki. 2019. <em>Killing Commendatore</em>. Anchor Canada.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>2023</category>
  <category>Haruki Murakami</category>
  <category>Japan</category>
  <category>Fiction</category>
  <guid>https://serhatbe.github.io/continuum/posts/2023-June-1/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
